<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Protect Lab</title>
    <link>/en/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/en/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Protect Lab 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/logo.svg</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/en/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dried Blood Spots</title>
      <link>/en/project/dried-blood-spots/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/project/dried-blood-spots/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-description&#34;&gt;Project Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modification of biomarkers through an internet-based intervention for depression in back pain patients on sick leave.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depression is a serious psychological condition that can have a devastating impact on patients, their family, friends and society. There is currently no laboratory test for this disorder, so patients often have to wait years for a diagnosis. During this time they do not receive the treatment and support they need. For this reason, we are developing a molecular test based on &amp;ldquo;Blood Spots&amp;rdquo; (i.e. dried drops of blood on filter paper). Such a test can provide an early and accurate diagnosis for patients with depression and help to get further assistance quickly. We measure the concentration of over 100 proteins in the dried blood drops. To do this, we use a technique called mass spectrometer analysis. The results of the study will be published.
​&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;funding--cooperation&#34;&gt;Funding &amp;amp; Cooperation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;banner.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Balance With Us</title>
      <link>/en/project/mit-uns-im-gleichgewicht/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/project/mit-uns-im-gleichgewicht/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-description&#34;&gt;Project Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental disorder prevention with Internet- and telephone-based interventions for persons in the &amp;ldquo;green professions &amp;ldquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model project &amp;ldquo;Mit uns im Gleichgewicht&amp;rdquo; (In Balance With Us), funded by the Social Insurance for Agriculture, Forestry and Horticulture (SVLFG), aims to promote and maintain mental health among farmers, foresters and horticulturists and is being scientifically evaluated by the Friedrich-Alexander University Erlangen-Nuremberg and the University of Ulm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to maintain and promote the mental health of farmers, foresters and horticulturists, the SVLFG offers the insured persons on-site preventive measures such as seminars on stress management. Within the framework of the model project, these offers will be expanded to include internet and tele-based interventions (online health training by the GET.ON Institute and intensive individual coaching by IVPNetworks). Interventions to prevent mental stress are particularly in demand in agriculture, as this occupational group is exposed to many stressors and strains due to difficult working conditions (e.g. high workload, family conflicts, seasonal work). It has been proven that internet and tele-based interventions can be effective, but the effects at population level depend on the actual use of the target group. With this background, there is a great need for scientifically sound knowledge about the needs of farmers, foresters and horticulturists, their partners and family members working with them, and how these needs can be met effectively. In addition, it should be examined whether target group-specific offers for this group of people can effectively and cost-effectively counteract the development of depressive disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chair of Clinical Psychology and Psychotherapy of the FAU, on behalf of SVLFG, is investigating in partly overlapping sub-projects the current use and acceptance of preventive interventions among farmers, gardeners and foresters on the one hand, and the effectiveness of two specific interventions (online-based health training, telemedical intensive care) on the other hand. In addition, the new health services and online-based interventions are being offered to SVLFG insured persons via different access routes as part of a large implementation study throughout Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Target group of the project&lt;/strong&gt;
Farmers insured with SVLFG, their co-insured partners and family members&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project duration&lt;/strong&gt;
01.06.2017 – 30.05.2021&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get.On Offline</title>
      <link>/en/project/geton-offline/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/project/geton-offline/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-description&#34;&gt;Project Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GET.On Offline is an online-based self-help training for coping with problematic internet usage. Problematic Internet usage can relate to computer games, social networks, but also to online sex, online shopping and online gambling. Where is the line between everyday use and problematic use? Problematic behavior begins when affected persons have an irresistible desire for the respective activities. Their thoughts and emotions are massively influenced by online offers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who use the Internet excessively begin to lose control over their use and, if they are denied access, withdrawal symptoms may occur. This can manifest itself, for example, in restlessness, nervousness or depressive mood. Tolerance can also develop and other important areas of life can be affected. Problematic Internet use thus has negative consequences in various areas. One may no longer pay attention to a healthy lifestyle or experience losses in professional or academic areas of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://geton-training.de/internetsucht-php/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Study Participation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;hek.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;200&#34;/&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ImpleMentAll</title>
      <link>/en/project/implementall/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/project/implementall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;projektbeschreibung&#34;&gt;Projektbeschreibung&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In den letzten zwei Jahrzehnten wurden große Anstrengungen in die Entwicklung, Testung und Implementation von eHealth für eine weite Bandbreite von Gesundheitsproblemen, im körperlichen wie im psychischen Bereich gesetzt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nichtsdestotrotz schaffen es wenige Interventionen in die Routinebehandlung, oder benötigen viele Jahre auf dem Weg dahin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ImpleMentAll (IMA) zielt darauf ab, durch die Entwicklung, Anwendung und Evaluation maßgeschneiderter Implementationsstrategien in einem natürlichen Labor derzeitiger eHealth-Implementationsintiviativen in der EU und darüber hinaus eine evidenzbasierte Antwort auf dieses Problem zu geben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Forschung des Projektes baut dabei auf vorhergegangenen internationalen Projekten auf (z.B. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://renewinghealth.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Renewing Health&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.e-compared.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;E-COMPARED&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mastermind-project.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MasterMind&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.implementall.eu/16-npt.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NPT&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.implementall.eu/17-nomad.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NoMAD&lt;/a&gt;, und 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.implementall.eu/18-mast.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MAST&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die laufenden Implementations-Initiativen, die die Basis für die Implementationforschung dieses Projektes bilden, basieren sämtlich auf internet-basierter kognitiver Verhaltenstherapie (iCBT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICBT-Implementationsprozesse werden derzeit auf der ganzen Welt durchgeführt. ImpleMentAll nutzt diese Projekte, um Werkzeuge zur Implementation von iCBT zu entwerfen, die eHealth effizienter machen sollen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ziele-des-projekts&#34;&gt;Ziele des Projekts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entwicklung eines generischen &amp;ldquo;Integrated Theory&amp;rdquo;-basierten Rahmens für Interventions-Anpassungen (ItFits-toolkit) zur datenbasierten Implementation evidenzbasierter eHealth-Dienstleistungen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstration der Vorteile des ItFits-toolkit auf die Implementation von eHealth für psychische Störungen (iCBT) in 9 europäischen Ländern und Australien&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dissemination des validierten Toolkits in verschiedenen Kontexten&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>StudiCare</title>
      <link>/en/project/studicare/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/en/project/studicare/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-description&#34;&gt;Project Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mental-health-promotion-in-college-students&#34;&gt;Mental Health Promotion in College Students&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StudiCare includes various online training courses for the prevention and treatment of mental illness, tailored to the needs of college students. In order to improve existing offers, the StudiCare panel regularly surveys undergraduate students at the Friedrich-Alexander-University and the University of Ulm about their mental well-being from the first semester onwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;College is a new stage of life in which students make the transition from adolescence to adulthood. This transition period is characterized by joyful experiences as well as new, stressful situations. These include, for example, looking for one&amp;rsquo;s own apartment, organizing finances and studies, finding new friends, getting used to a new environment, exam stress, etc. In the course of their studies, students are not only confronted with this new situation, but may also experience crises. In combination with possible risk behaviors, such as excessive consumption of alcohol or cannabis, this can lead to exhaustion, psychosomatic complaints, anxiety and depressive disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;studicare-panel&#34;&gt;StudiCare Panel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web-based panel survey is conducted in numerous countries worldwide as part of the WHO The World Mental Health Survey Initiative under the coordination of Harvard University among students from the first semester onwards. The aim of the survey is to obtain information on the mental health of students as well as on risk and protective factors for emotional stress during their undergraduate studies. In addition, more information on the willingness and barriers to using psychosocial interventions and counseling services will be collected. With information from the surveys, the need for help and support services will be assessed, existing counseling services will be improved and new online-based interventions tailored to the individual needs of students will be developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;studicare-online-health-trainings&#34;&gt;StudiCare Online Health Trainings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The online health training courses from StudiCare are low-threshold structured self-help training courses. These trainings can improve the well-being of students and alleviate complaints in a wide variety of areas. They can be used independently of time and place, can be optimally integrated into the individual daily routine and can be conducted anonymously. In the training courses, students manage their complaints independently by working through numerous modules. Modules are based on cognitive-behavioral techniques that are also used in conventional psychotherapy. Essential here are various practical exercises such as relaxation techniques, protocols for self-observation and the integration of small exercises into everyday life (&amp;ldquo;tiny task&amp;rdquo;). These help to reduce negative behavior and build up positive behavior. In the course of the project, new trainings are continuously being developed that deal with topics that are relevant for students. The newly developed online health trainings will be examined in randomized clinical studies to evaluate their effectiveness and cost-effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;www.studicare.com&#34;&gt;Training Participation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;evidence-based-methods-for-promoting-mental-health-among-students-series-of-meta-analytical-reviews&#34;&gt;Evidence-based methods for promoting mental health among students: Series of meta-analytical reviews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to derive appropriate measures, a comprehensive assessment of the current evidence base of psychosocial support services is necessary. In a series of meta-analytical reviews, the current knowledge about effective psychological treatment and prevention services including their effectiveness is collected and critically examined. Psychological interventions and their effectiveness are examined with regard to specific disorder areas (e.g. anxiety symptoms, eating disorders, sleep disorders, suicidal tendencies) or intervention methods (e.g. internet-based procedures, &amp;ldquo;third wave&amp;rdquo; procedures). Along with clinical effectiveness, special attention is devoted to the influence of interventions on the academic impairment of students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;promotion--cooperation&#34;&gt;Promotion &amp;amp; Cooperation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BARMER, Bergische Universität Wuppertal, European Union, FernUniversität in Hagen,
FOM University, Harvard Medical School, Leuphana University of Lüneburg, Minddistrict, RWTH Aachen University,
University Jaume I, University of Ulm, University of Zurich, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam,
World Health Organization&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;logos.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;501&#34;/&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
